<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eirēnogonia, or The pedegree of peace deliuered in a sermon intended to the iudges at the assises holden at Okeham in Rutland, Iuly 31. 1629. but after vpon an occasion, preached at Vppingham, in the same countie, Septemb. 6. 1629. By Antony Fawkner, Master of Arts, late student in Jesus Colledge at Oxford.</title>
            <author>Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2006</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 791:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eirēnogonia, or The pedegree of peace deliuered in a sermon intended to the iudges at the assises holden at Okeham in Rutland, Iuly 31. 1629. but after vpon an occasion, preached at Vppingham, in the same countie, Septemb. 6. 1629. By Antony Fawkner, Master of Arts, late student in Jesus Colledge at Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Robert Allott, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The pedegree of peace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2006:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2006:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΕΙΡΗΝΟΓΟΝΙΑ; OR THE PEDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GREE OF PEACE, DELIVERED IN A SERMON INTENDED TO THE IVDGES AT THE ASSISES holden at <hi>Okeham</hi> in <hi>Rutland,</hi> Iuly. 31. 1629. but after vpon an occaſion, preached at <hi>Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingham,</hi> in the ſame Countie, <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb.</hi> 6. 1629.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Antony Fawkner,</hi> Maſter of Arts, late Student in <hi>Jeſus</hi> Colledge at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 89.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Righteouſneſſe and equity are the ſtabliſhment of his Throne.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 119.72.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Law of thy mouth is better vnto me then thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſilver.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVK. 22.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Peace be vnto you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for <hi>Robert Allot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard at the ſigne of the Beare. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2006:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2006:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL MY LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VING VNCLE, MASTER EVERARD FAWKNER, Peace Internall and Externall from God the Author of Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the time of your Shrief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, you requeſted this enſuing labour, which I was ready at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to haue payd as the tribute, not ſo much of my courteſie, as duty. It was intended for your eare, but (by I know not what preuention twice or thrice put off) J pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it now (what ere it is) to your and the Worlds eye. Which is a doctrinall ſenſe too, and by ſo much the more criticall then the eare, by how much the more curious, and indeed can
<pb facs="tcp:2006:3"/> better ſatisfie its owne quaintneſſe by a priue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it hath to dwell longer on its obiect. But for my owne part, J quaile not for any <hi>Momus.</hi> I haue been ſo well acquainted with the worlds folly, that J ſcorne either to flatter, or feare it. I haue knowne it requite fawning with flouting: and he that clawes it, had beſt take heede that it kicke not him. Such is its dotage, that for the more part it plants its prime flowers in dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils, not gardens. So that he who dreames to purchaſe her fauour by deſerts, doth but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> make roapes of ſand; a labour foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, becauſe fruitleſſe. Yea this I dare ſay, that he of our calling (though it be moſt excellent) which by his laudable indeauours alone, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in theſe laſt and worſt dayes to gaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, ſhall with expectation, hunger, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy make himſelfe ſo leane, that (vnleſſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be more indulgent, then charity harborous) hee ſhall ſcarce euer bee able by all his gaines to put himſelfe in fleſh againe. So much, and no more honesty may we expect from the World in its downe-right Nature, and as little or leſſe from its vailed, hypocriticall, and whining ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie. <hi>Experto crede.</hi> Wherefore if the beſt
<pb facs="tcp:2006:3"/> deſerts can hope for no better, I haue ſmall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by my weakeſt endeauours to expect ſo much, vnleſſe (as indeed it oft happens in this croſſe world) the ſillier fellow may haue the better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Briefly, I lye ſo almoſt leuell with the earth, that <hi>Non habeo vndè cadam,</hi> I cannot fall much lower. Wherefore I feare no cenſure; not becauſe I am aboue any enuy, but becauſe in the ſecurity of a ſhrub from the winde, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath all. As for you Sir, to whom I offer this poore piece in its homely proportion, ſhapen to a Country Auditory, if it offend you, reiect it, for euen ſo you ſhall not diſpleaſe me, or (which J wiſh) if it pleaſe you reade it, and in it</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poore Kinſeman in all Chriſtian ſeruice to be commanded, <hi>Antony Fawkner.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2006:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2006:4"/>
            <head>ΕΙΡΗΝΟΓΟΝΙΑ, OR THE PEDEGREE OF PEACE, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LEVIT. 24.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>His Mothers name alſo was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the Tribe of Dan.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Atures perfection preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth an imperfection. Inſtants are too nimble for her ſober determination, and her actions for the more part are accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a graduall motion. Art receiues, and imitates her method, firſt hewing her worke in the rough, ere ſhe can put to <hi>vltimam manum,</hi> her finiſhing, her exact hand. And ſee how the Diuell will bee Ape to them both; he muſt haue his Climax too, aſcending from the conception of a ſinne to its birth, from its birth, to its maturitie. Diſcord boakes to equall contention, contention ſwelles to the greatneſſe of a quarrell, then by its owne poyſon burſts in Death.<note place="margin">22. <hi>q.</hi> 37, 38, 41.</note> Tis the Schoolemans
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2006:5"/> gradation from the infancy of malice to its age, from the beginning to the end. Tis conceiued in the heart, brought forth by the tongue, executed by the hand, and receiues its iuſt vengeance in its ſelfe-deſtruction. We need not ſtray farre to find an example; my Text affoords a wretched one, the ſonne of an Egyptian; <hi>who firſt went out,</hi> verſ. 10. Lo, his heart was full. Then <hi>he ſtroue,</hi> againe verſ. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Septuagint, <hi>Iurgatus eſt,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> renders it, he brawled. His tongue would be the Midwife to bring to the birth that miſchiefe, which his heart had determined. And it is like, had not preuention hindred, what paſſion threatned, there would haue been ſome knocks. Or at the leaſt, ſuppoſe the hands bloody execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be preuented; then will the tongue ſupply its place, and ſo challenge a double ſhare in guilt. For <hi>Maledixit, he curſed.</hi> Yea, and becauſe his hand might not wound him, whom his tongue had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled, <hi>Coelum ipſum petijt ſtultitiâ;</hi> God muſt be the obiect of his malice, as well as his neighbour; for <hi>blaſphemauit Nomen Domini: Hee blaſphemed the Name of the Lord,</hi> ver. 11. And what now can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? The ſin is ſwolne to its compleat to its, ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched hugeneſſe: then it muſt needs burſt. Iuſtice will auenge, they brought him vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> verſ. 11. and vengeance will reward, they ſtoned him, verſ. 14. So then, the tranſgreſſour is dead, but not the ſinne; or if the ſinne, yet not the ſhame. There are two fames in the fiction, good and euill, each equally perpetuall. Happy are the good, if their fame bee eternall, and as vnhappy are the bad, if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2006:5"/> theirs be more then momentany. The memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the Iuſt is as a ſweet odour; <hi>Illîc Naſcuntur violae:</hi> the memorie of the wicked repaires, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiues their ignominies, which otherwiſe would decay, and lye dead, as their forgotten carkeiſes. Nay, ſo ſelfe-diffuſiue is this opprobry of ſinne, that tis not limited to the tranſgreſſours perſon, but as more infectious then the contagion of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie ſpreads it ſelfe at once ouer both Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Poſterity. If the Father tread awry, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The children ſhall be ſure to taſte the ſhame, perchance the puniſhment. <hi>Achan</hi> ſinned: he and his whole family periſhed: <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Haman</hi> tranſgreſſed: he and his ten ſonnes were vtterly deſtroyed: <hi>Eſth.</hi> 9.10.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So perilous is the company of the vngodly, and ſo full of danger alliance to the wicked. Nor is it more vnhappineſſe to bee the ſonne of a wicked father, then to be the father of a rebellious childe. When the Blaſphemer in my Text curſed, haply <hi>Shelomith</hi> was dead, tis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that <hi>Dibri</hi> was, and that <hi>Dan</hi> was, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: yet, as if there had been a ſecret vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe due to haue been inflicted vpon them for the mutuall relation betweene their very aſhes, and their accurſed ſeede, they muſt vndergoe the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, to bee recorded the misfortunate pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of ſo graceleſſe a ſonne: yea, ſo exact is the regiſter, that it catalogues from the neereſt of Kin to the firſt of the Tribe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His mothers name alſo was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri of the Tribe of Dan.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2006:6"/>
            <p>Affectation of method is the confuſion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. Wherefore not to tire, or fright you (as with ſo many <hi>Hydraes</hi> heads) with tedious Hep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacotomies, nor to delude your apprehenſions with ſubtile curioſities as vaine and brittle, as they are thinne. Briefly, my Text includes a threefold diſquiparant relation. The firſt (according to the order of words) is <hi>inter matrem &amp; filium,</hi> betweene the mother and the ſonne: <hi>Shelomith</hi> and the <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>Inter Patrem &amp; Filiam;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the father and the daughter; <hi>Dibri &amp; She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomith.</hi> The third is <hi>inter Patrem &amp; Filium;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the father and the ſonne; <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Dibri.</hi> This we may obſerue from the hiſtoricall Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie; in which againe, if with a ſharpe eye wee but looke into the vailed treaſure of the names ſignification, wee may diſcouer the like relation included in a genealogie myſticall. Let then ſo hainous a tranſgreſſor as this blaſphemer, bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the abſtract for his tranſgreſſion, ſinne. Whoſe ſonne is he? <hi>Shelomiths.</hi> What is ſhee? The Interpreter tranſlates her,<note place="margin">Paguin. de Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Nom. Heb.</note> Peacefull, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [<hi>Shalom</hi>] Peace. Aſcend next to her father, <hi>Dibri,</hi> which the Tranſlator renders, My Word, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [<hi>Dabar</hi> or <hi>Dibber</hi>] a Word; a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or vnwritten word, the two diuiding mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Lex,</hi> a Law. The Scripture iuſtifies the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; <hi>Ho wrote on the Tables according to the firſt writing, the ten Words: Deut</hi> 10.4. The <hi>Words,</hi> that is, <hi>the Commandements,</hi> which are <hi>The Law.</hi> Climbe yet a few ſteps higher, and from thence in a faire proſpect, view the Anceſtor of <hi>Dibri:</hi> he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2006:6"/> is <hi>Dan.</hi> Holy-writ conſtrueth him <hi>Iudging,</hi> a <hi>Iudge,</hi> or <hi>Iudgement:</hi> for firſt, his reputed mother gaue him that name with her bleſſing; <hi>And Rachel ſaid, God hath iudged me, therefore called ſhe his name Dan: Gen.</hi> 30.6. And againe, <hi>Iacob</hi> confirmed it with his bleſſing; <hi>Dan ſhall iudge his people: Geneſ.</hi> 49.16. Deſcend then in the right line of this Genealogy: <hi>Dan</hi> is the father of <hi>Dibri; Iudgement of the Law: Dibri</hi> begets <hi>Shelomith;</hi> the <hi>Law, Peace:</hi> and <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomith</hi> is the parent of the <hi>Blaſphemer; Peace</hi> brings forth <hi>tranſgreſsion. Dan</hi> begets <hi>Dibri;</hi> againe, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri, Shelomith;</hi> and <hi>Shelomith</hi> beares the <hi>Curſer. Iudgement</hi> procreates the <hi>Law;</hi> the <hi>Law, Peace;</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> brings forth her miſhapen off-ſpring, <hi>Sinne.</hi> Old <hi>Heſiod,</hi> whether benefited by the twy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Nature, or fortunate by a luckie ſtumble in the Heatheniſh darkeneſſe, in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Heſiod. in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</note> groaped at the ſhadow of this Genealogie. He makes <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> three Siſters, the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of one Mother, <hi>Themis,</hi> or <hi>Iustice,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But we leaue the Tale to the Poets patronage, returning to their mutuall and ſucceſſiue generation in my Text: in which leauing the order of words in the aſcent from <hi>Shelomith,</hi> we will begin at the further end, and ſo <hi>in lineâ rectâ deſcendente,</hi> paſſe downeward from the father to the children; firſt, touching him which was firſt by the <hi>priority of Nature</hi> and <hi>Time, Honour</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and he is</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Dan, Iudgement.</head>
               <p>Iudgement is the act of Iuſtice.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 60. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> Iuſtice an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2006:7"/> by which we haue an inclination,<note place="margin">Aquin. in AR. Ethic. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> power and will to the performance of what is iuſt: ſo the Philoſopher.<note place="margin">Iuſtinian. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. &amp; Iure.</note> Or, as the Imperial Lawyer (though not ſo formally) it is <hi>Conſtans &amp; perpetua voluntas ſuum cuique tribuens;</hi> a conſtant and perſeuering will;<note place="margin">Georg. Reiſch. Margarit. Philoſopn. lib. <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> or more Logically, the habit of that will, which giues, and by which, each one receiues his proper and peculiar right. Now wee know, that Habits are by ſo much the firmer radicated in their ſubiects, by how much the actions from whence they flow, are the more frequently and timely vſed.<note place="margin">Horat. epiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſeruabit odorem Teſta diu;</hi> The vpright tree was made ſtreight when it was a ſprigge. Vertues that are taught to youth, grow habituall to age; and what Nature can neuer find eaſie, cuſtome make natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Wherefore the Perſians, that they might be ſure to prouide vpright <hi>Iudges,</hi> made their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren petty <hi>Iuſtices,</hi> and taught them <hi>Law</hi> as ſoone as letters.<note place="margin">Xenophon. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> They went to the <hi>Schoole of Iuſtice</hi> euery day, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Xenophon,</hi> as duly as amongſt vs our Nouices to learne their firſt rudiments. Yea, their very ſports were ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and (as another ſmall Commonweale) they had their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Publike Halles to moote their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Caſes in. So would they wiſely preuent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by their diſcipline, accompanying their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of yeeres with a growth of vertue, that they might become <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>iuſt</hi> both together. What the light of <hi>Nature</hi> taught them,<note place="margin">Horrt. carm. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ed. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of <hi>God</hi> commanded the Iewes. <hi>Eradenda cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidineis Parui ſunt elementa.</hi> They were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2006:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A ſtiffe-necked people of an vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed heart, Act.</hi> 7.51. and the coare of their rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be grubbed vp from the roote, which is eaſieſt done in the Spring of youth, when ſinne can take but tender hold, wherefore they muſt <hi>teach Gods Lawes diligently vnto their children,</hi> and to make them more habituall, they muſt <hi>talke of them when they are in their houſes, and when they walke by the way, and when they lie downe, and when they riſe vp: Deut.</hi> 6.7. yea, they muſt <hi>binde them as a ſigne vpon their hands, and as Frontlets betweene their eyes:</hi> Verſ. 8. Whence the Phariſes as ſeeming-perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the Law, wrote thoſe ſentences in Front<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-parchments, which they ſhould haue grauen in their hearts, and miſplaced their conſciences in their Philacteries: <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.5. Nor is it won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that a gemme ſo precious ſhould be in ſo high eſteeme.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 58. <hi>art.</hi> 4.</note> For indeed Nature knowing her Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal to be of God, hath exalted her vnto a throne at leaſt, for the more part aboue the reſt of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. Her ſeate is not in the lower appetite of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> but in that ſupreme one of the <hi>Will,</hi> which being a faculty of the diuiner part of man, is the moſt conuenient receptacle of a vertue, whoſe originall is ſo Diuine. Diuine? Yes: for Iuſtice is of the Lord, yea tis the Lords. <hi>He executed the Iuſtice of the Lord: Deut.</hi> 33.21. <hi>Heare then, O Iſrael, The Lord our God is one Lord: Deut.</hi> 6.4. and that <hi>Lord both mercifull and iuſt: Pſal.</hi> 116.5. <hi>Plato</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that hee was attended by a reuenging Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which executed his wrath vpon the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours of his Law, and in that was more religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2006:8"/> then the accurſed <hi>Marcion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iren. adverſ. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſet, lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> a blaſphemer at leaſt, equall with the ſonne of the Egyptian, diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Diuinity into two Godheads. The one forſooth he called Good, and ſtiled him, The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Mercy: the other Bad, and reputes him the Patrone of Iuſtice. As if he would make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Iuſtice vtter enemies, and by an vniuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence depriue Iuſtice of her goodnes. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in the power of the Spirit mightily confutes him,<note place="margin">Iren. adverſ. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſes, lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>42.43.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates him as guilty of contradiction as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, vnder whoſe victorious feete wee leaue him cloathed with ſhame and confuſion of face, mocking his fooliſh Theſis, as apparently repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the firſt principles of Philoſophy, as The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologie, with a Poets fiction, weighty enough to contrapoiſe his ſlender poſition;<note place="margin">Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Iudgement is the daughter of the moſt high God, indeed it is the worke of the Almighty: <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.24. And becauſe God ſaith ſo, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is bold to ſay as much, with as cloſe a tye, knitting the reſt of vertues vnto Iuſtice, as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher can binde them vnto Prudence: for <hi>Non aliter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quis fiet bonus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiph. cont. Haroſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſi non fuerit Iuſtus:</hi> if a man cannot be iuſt, it is impoſſible that he ſhould bee good. To diuide honeſty from vertue, and goodneſſe from iuſtice, are equally <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reach of poſſibility. And that it is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,<note place="margin">Adrianus Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebus aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Coryphaeus</hi> of our Moderne Criticks (not to talke of <hi>Ariſtotles Media</hi>) induceth <hi>Vlpian</hi> to conclude from the definition of Iuſtice, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is <hi>voluntas conſtans &amp; perpetua;</hi> A conſtant and perpetuall Will: ſo Stoically both arguing it to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2006:8"/> be a vertue, and diſtinguiſhing it from the pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations mutability, by a ſolid, fixed, and perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring conſtancie: yea in one eminent acceptation,<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>22.</hi> q. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.</hi> art. <hi>6.</hi> in corpore.</note> in regard of her generall direction, ſhe may iuſtly be ſtiled, <hi>Omnis virtus,</hi> The whole vniuerſalitie of vertues, as guiding them al to the common good, as charity directs them to the Diuine Good. All which may challenge their euidence from the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Iuſtice: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Aquin. in Ariſt. Ethic. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> lect. <hi>1.</hi> Ambroſ. lib. Offic.</note> 
                  <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cuique tribuere;</hi> to giue euery one his owne; to God and Man, and to Man and Man. S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> addes, <hi>Alienum non vendicare, propriam vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem negligere vt communem aequalitatem cuſtodiat:</hi> Not to lay claime to our neighbours goods, but to preferre the generall equitie, yea to our owne profit. Loe then, beloued, <hi>Iuſtitia tribuit, &amp;c.</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice giues what is due, ſhe doth not ſell it. Iuſt weights poyze her ballance, not a heauy purſe: and to declare her innocency concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the Thebans painted her without hands;<note place="margin">Plutarch. in Iſide. Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Iuſtice is a Virgin, pure, immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, vndefiled, incorrupt: wherefore it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſhe ſhould aſſociate her ſelf with baſe mony-gods, whoſe gaine is their godlineſſe, and are therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>corrupt in minde,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. <hi>&amp; Spirituall Fornicatours, for their hearts haue gone a whoring from the Lord: Eccleſ.</hi> 46.11. Wherefore <hi>Vlpian</hi> doubts not to ſtile honeſt Lawyers <hi>Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Iustitiae;</hi> the Prieſts of Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Turneb. aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> emulus (as <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebus</hi> coniectures) of the Stoicks ſincere wiſe man,<note place="margin">Irenaeus aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus haereſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> to whom onely they vouchſafed the title of a Prieſt. And doth not <hi>Iraeneus</hi> aſtipulate? <hi>Omnes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2006:9"/> Iuſti Sacerdotalem habent ordinem;</hi> Let any expound the word <hi>Iuſti</hi> in as large and generall ſenſe as hee may, yet in this I ſuppoſe I erre not. The inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of a righteous Iudge may adde vnto his Honour the reuerend title, at leaſt of a <hi>Lay-Prieſt:</hi> ſuch a proportionall Anallogie betweene their Callings is grounded vpon the vprightneſſe of their actions. It was death amongſt the Romans to receiue a bribe, eſpecially in a cauſe of death. Yea, the Acilian Law did proſecute this ſharpe decree againſt the perſon accuſed, with ſuch iuſt ſeuerity,<note place="margin">Pompon. Laetus de Legib. <hi>1.5.</hi>
                  </note> that there was admitted no <hi>Iuſiitium,</hi> no <hi>Dies Iuſtus,</hi> but he was immediately condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>ſine ampliatione aut comperendinatione,</hi> without any delay of Demurre, Adiourning Court, or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of repriue. I need not tell you, how <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> faſtened corrupt <hi>Sandoces</hi> to the tormenting Croſſe;<note place="margin">Barnab. Briſoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de reg. Perſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> nor how <hi>Cambyſes</hi> cauſed <hi>Siſamnes</hi> skin to be plucked off, and ſpread vpon the Iudges chaire, placing his ſonne firſt in it, that by the balefull ſpectacle of his fathers hide, hee might be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from peruerting Iuſtice by receiuing bribes. Wherefore hauing ſpoken of this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, very briefly, yet as much as needs, my theame being ſtill of Iuſtice and Iudgement, I paſſe vnto two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconueniences in their adminiſtration; Too ſudden expedition and delay. From the firſt of which,<note place="margin">Epiph. lib. <hi>11.</hi> c. de Manichaeis.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> teſtifies, the Perſians to bee ſo free, that in the moſt capitall offences they were ſlow to puniſh; ſuppoſing that in cauſes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning life, no time was long <hi>propeque eſſe vt lubenter condemnent qui cito,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Barnab. Briſon. de reg. Perſ. li. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Briſſonius</hi> amplifies: They
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2006:9"/> thought the condemnation halfe voluntary, and conſequently vniuſt, if very ſudden. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from a Rabbi,<note place="margin">Targum Ionath. Mumb. <hi>9 8</hi> c</note> that there were foure cauſes brought vnto <hi>Moſes:</hi> two were reſpectiuely of ſmall moment, in which he made haſte; one was the matter of vncleanneſſe, keeping from the Paſſeouer, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.9. the other was the caſe of <hi>Zelophebads</hi> daughters concerning their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Numb.</hi> 36.10. The other two were of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter weight, as touching life and death, in which he delayed. The firſt was the matter of the Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, in my Text: the ſecond, that of him that brake the Sabbath in gathering ſticks, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.35. yet in none of all theſe caſes was there more haſte then good ſpeed, for in them all (ſaith my Author) <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwered, <hi>Non audiui,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Godwin. Moſes &amp; Aaron. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> I haue not heard, to wit, from the Lord, intimating, that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration ought to accompany iudgement, &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence not to bee pronounced, before conſultation with God. For concerning all theſe caſes the Lord ſpake vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in the leaſt of them, the Lawgiuer ſolemnely beſpeakes the people to <hi>ſtand ſtill, &amp; ego audiam, and I will heare what the Lord will command: Numb.</hi> 9.8. On the contrarie, as deliberation is requiſite, ſo voluntary delayes are dangerous. What iniuſtice doe we reade of in the vnrighteous Iudge, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.6. ſaue onely delay? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: The ſooner the Cockle is deſtroyed, the better the Corne will grow. The Royall Iudge, <hi>Dauid,</hi> knew it, when he ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Betimes, early,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sophocles in Electrá.</note> 
                  <hi>in the morning will I deſtroy the wicked of the Land: Pſ.</hi> 101.8. By this then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2006:10"/> it is manifeſt, that Iuſtice giues <hi>freely, deliberately,</hi> and (as the caſe requires) <hi>ſpeedily.</hi> The next <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> is, What ſhe giues? Her proper Obiect <hi>Ius,</hi> or <hi>Iuſtum, What is right and due.</hi> Doe you inquire what that is? the Schooleman defines it to bee <hi>Opus adaequatum alteri ſecundum aliquem aequalitatis modum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 57. <hi>art.</hi> 1, 2.</note> An action ſquared and proportioned to anothers benefit or loſſe, according to the equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of deſert. Now this equalitie ariſeth either <hi>ex naturâ rei,</hi> from <hi>the nature of the thing:</hi> as if I lend ſo much, from the principles of Nature in a Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Syllogiſme, conſcience concludes, that ſo much is to be reſtored againe: or elſe this adequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or equality proceedeth <hi>ex condicto,</hi> from <hi>a mutuall agreement,</hi> which againe is either <hi>priuate,</hi> betwixt perſon and perſon; or <hi>publike,</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, and vnanimous agreement of the publike Magiſtrate and people. From the firſt ariſeth the iudgement betweene <hi>priuate contracts;</hi> from the ſecond, that concerning <hi>publike Edicts.</hi> It followes then,<note place="margin">Xenophon. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Iuſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects an <hi>equalitie;</hi> and that equalitie intimates a twofold <hi>proportion:</hi> one is <hi>inter rem &amp; rem:</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the traffike and the value, about which the <hi>commutatiue</hi> part of Iuſtice is conuerſant:<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>22.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> Ariſt. Eth. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>inter rem &amp; perſonam,</hi> betweene the Perſon deſeruing, and the Reward, which by an equall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution is adapted,<note place="margin">Barnab. Briſſon. de Reg. Perſ. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> or fitted to the perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, by that other ſubiectiue part of <hi>Iustice,</hi> to wit, <hi>Diſtributiue.</hi> The Perſians religiouſly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both parts, but iuſt <hi>Ariſtides</hi> extols them for the latter;<note place="margin">Ariſtid. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2006:10"/> They requited not a multitude of honourable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts with few gifts, nor great deſerts with ſmal rewards. And loe, the Precept of the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands both parts: <hi>Iuſt ballances, iuſt weights, a iuſt Ephah, and a iuſt Hin ſhall yee haue: Leuit.</hi> 19.36. and <hi>the Labourer is worthy of his hire: Luk.</hi> 10.7. From theſe are euident the <hi>definition</hi> of this <hi>Ius,</hi> or right, and it is <hi>neceſsity.</hi> This is that <hi>Palladium,</hi> that Image of <hi>Pallas,</hi> that Statue of Iuſtice fallen downe from Heauen into our Common-wealth, which being religiouſly preſerued, our Cities are conſerued from hoſtile violence: and vpon whoſe violation, Iuſtice it ſelfe immediately, or at leaſt by a ſudden conſequence receiues the afront, and the reaſon is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>He that iniures the picture,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Georg. Hemiſ. in Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ex Proclo.</note> 
                  <hi>reproacheth the perſon whoſe the picture is; now this</hi> Iuſtum, <hi>or Right, is the liuely image, the true protraiture of Iuſtice:</hi> which as ſhe renders what is <hi>Ius,</hi> or Right, ſo to each one <hi>Ius ſuum,</hi> what is his <hi>owne, proper, and peculiar right.</hi> In matters of poſſeſſion Iuſtice takes not notice of conueniency, but <hi>Due.</hi> It preſerues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and that iuſtly; yea oft-times to the bad, not becauſe he deſerues it, but becauſe tis <hi>his.</hi> That Story of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> when he was a boy, is as vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as elegant: Being at the Schoole of Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Xenoph <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whereof wee ſpake before, it was his turne to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide a controuerſie betweene two of his play fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, the one being a great boy that had a little coate, the other being a little boy that had a great coate, and one at ſtrife for the others garment. He, as hee thought moſt conuenient, iudged that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2006:11"/> both ſhould change, ſentencing the larger coate to the bigger Lad, and the leſſer to the ſmaller. But what followes? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee was puniſhed by his Tutor, to make him remember, that Iuſtice reſpects the <hi>right of poſſeſsion,</hi> more then the <hi>conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency:</hi> it giues to each man what is his <hi>peculiar owne by Law:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Wherefore the Iudge ought not to ſquare his ſentence by ſeeming expediency, but by the Law.</hi> Hence it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that the goodneſſe of Iuſtice is not termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in the perſon of the iuſt adminiſtratour, but as more ſelfe-communicatiue then the reſt of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, extends her benefits <hi>ad alterum,</hi> to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of others; yea, <hi>ad omnes,</hi> euen vnto all; for ſhe giues whats due <hi>vnicuique,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Iſide.</note> 
                  <hi>to euery one.</hi> She reſpects no perſons, for ſhe ſees them not. The Thebanes painted her without eyes: or if ſhee haue any, they are not in her owne, but in the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges head: for him indeed <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſtiles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Seeing-Law.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Xenophon. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But how? Marry he hath an eye to ſee, but not to pitie: an eye of vnderſtanding to ſearch out the ſinne, not an eye of partiality to fauour the delinquent. Reſpect of perſons then is the reiection of Iuſtice, and by it wee may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Iudges: But of what? Of equity? No: but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of euill thoughts: Iam.</hi> 2.4. From theſe then we may of a truth perceiue, that <hi>God is no accepter of perſons: Act.</hi> 10.34. Yea, the poore whom God ſeemes moſt to pitie, and for whoſe reliefe (as <hi>Philo</hi> with admiration of his Iuſtice notes) he hath left vnto his people ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and excitements to Mercy and compaſſion,<note place="margin">Philo Iudaeus de officio Iudicis.</note>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2006:11"/> euen they (I ſay) are excluded from all commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in iudgement, and that by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe prohibition: <hi>Thou ſhalt not countenance a poore man in his cauſe: Exod.</hi> 23.3. Hence of ſo glorious eſteeme in ancient time was this impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall iuſtice, that the Poet calles it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">Homer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dyſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The iudgement of the moſt diuine Kings.</hi> And loe, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> by warrant from the holy Ghoſt, is bold to ſet the ſame Crowne of glory on her head, terming her <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>The Royall Law: Iam.</hi> 2.8. And indeed why not a Royall Law,<note place="margin">Theod. Beza in loc. cit.</note> if a Law ſo ſupremely generall? For the performance of it, is the performance of the Law. I coniecture Saint <hi>Iames</hi> thought ſo, when hee made a direct <hi>Antitheſis</hi> betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Acceptation of perſons, and loue to our neighbour, which is the performance of the Law, Ro.</hi> 13.9, 10. His words are theſe: <hi>If ye ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the Royall Law, according to the Scripture, Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, yee doe well:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>But if yee accept perſons, yee commit ſinne, and are conuinced of the Law as tranſgreſſours: Iam.</hi> 2.8, 9. Hitherto (Beloued) I haue ſhadowed Iuſtice, and conſequently Iudgement (though with a ſlubbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Pencill) together with their properties, and haue prooued each of them to be ſeuerall Canons of Gods Law. I appeale then, as well to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of your reaſon as your faith, whether <hi>Dibri</hi> be of the Tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> whether Iudgement be the Father of the</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Law. Dibri.</head>
               <p>The diuiſion of the Law in generall into <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2006:12"/> Naturall</hi> and <hi>Humane,</hi> or <hi>Poſitiue:</hi> with the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall</hi> of the <hi>Poſitiue</hi> from the <hi>Naturall,</hi> and of that from the <hi>Eternall,</hi> I haue already heretofore in this place handled. At which time I alſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted the ſtrict tie, by which our conſcience is bound to the obſeruation of this <hi>Humane Law,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the dutie of Magiſtrates, who ought to proportion their Iudgements according to the rule of this Law: it being the beſt commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>Mandana</hi> could affoord her husband <hi>Cambyſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Xenoph. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>He made not his will a Law, but the Law his will, and ruled beſt, becauſe hee would be ruled.</hi> She ſayd ſo to her young ſonne, <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> and it ſeemes hee gaue good eare and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation to the commendations: for when himſelfe was after inueſted in his dignitie, he confeſſed the law to be a ſchoolemiſtris both to Magiſtrate and People; teaching them two leſſons, to each, one, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">Xenoph. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>The Art of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the Magiſtrate, the rule of Obedience to the Subiect.</hi> It is true indeede, that the Law had once its infancy, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rulers wil by neceſſity for want of Law ſtood for a Law: <hi>Semiramis</hi> decrees had the force of Law amongſt the Babylonians,<note place="margin">Briſſ. de Keg. Perſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> yea euen in oeconomicall &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate families, the father of the families word had the full vertue of Law. <hi>Iudah</hi> pronounced the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death againſt his daughter in Law, <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar: Bring her forth and let her be burnt: Gen.</hi> 38.24. So that <hi>Polydore Virgils</hi> coniecture may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, at leaſt probable, to wit, that written Lawes were not in vſe in <hi>Homers</hi> time,<note place="margin">Polid. Virgil. de Inuent. Rer, li. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> for <hi>in all his workes</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>he not ſo much as names a Law.</hi> Yet there
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2006:12"/> was euen then without controuerſie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, though not written, compoſed and publike edicts or conſtitutions, yet certaine receiued Traditions agreeing with the Law of Nature, equiualent in proportion with a Law. Such as were intimated by the ſame Authors <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Hom. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pelid. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. Rer. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Iuſtice of Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, or retribution of like for like.</hi> But after the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der times of Barbariſme had put off their rugged coate,<note place="margin">Demoſt. cont. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtogitonem.</note> 
                  <hi>Draco</hi> and <hi>Solon</hi> brought this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſo their Oratour ſtiles it) <hi>this diuine inuention</hi> of the Law firſt to Athens from whence the Romanes after brought their twelue tables well neare 300.<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſ. lib. <hi>10.</hi> Ab. vrb. condit. <hi>293.</hi> Glarean. in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropij, lib. <hi>1.</hi> an. <hi>291.</hi>
                  </note> yeres <hi>ab vrbe conditâ:</hi> from the beginning of their ſtate. So diuers Law-giuers furniſhed diuers Common-wealths, as <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ours (for why ſhould wee forget our owne?) <hi>Mulmutius Dunwallo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. Stow Chron. Ang.</note> and the renowned Lady <hi>Mercia,</hi> the Royall foundreſſe of our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Lawes Before all which,<note place="margin">Flau. Ioſep. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trâ Appion. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ioſephus</hi> iuſtly vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates antiquity to the Hebrew Lawes, the only abſolute and iuſt Decrees: <hi>Laetus</hi> calls them,<note place="margin">Pomp. Laetus de legib. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Coelo lapſas: Fallen from heauen:</hi> and indeed they of all the reſt were written with the <hi>finger of God. Exod.</hi> 31.18. This is that vndefiled Law,<note place="margin">Xenop. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the rule and ſquare of all humane Decrees, by which wee are made <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Ciuiler and better: for the Law of the Lord is perfect, conuerting the ſoule. Pſalm.</hi> 19.7. Nor indeed is it a wonder that the Law ſhould better vs, for it cuts off tranſgreſſion as its Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall enemie, ſith the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>Order,</hi> the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> meerely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Diſorder.</hi> This is that diuine decree to which, as to that of Nature if the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2006:13"/> reſt be conformable,<note place="margin">Horat. de Art. Poëticâ. Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quius in loc. citat. Pompon. Laetus de Legib. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> we may <hi>Leges incidere ligno ingraue them in wood or braſſe</hi> as eternally &amp; inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably to be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rued. But if they are diſſentient from this Law, they can neither <hi>Imperare, Vetare Punire,</hi> nor <hi>Permittere:</hi> nor <hi>Command</hi> nor <hi>Forbid,</hi> nor <hi>Puniſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 12. <hi>q.</hi> 95. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> nor <hi>Permit,</hi> depriued of the foure royall prerogatiues of iuſt Decrees: for they are not <hi>Leges,</hi> but <hi>Legum corruptiones: not Lawes but the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Lawes:</hi> And <hi>Woe vnto them that decree them, Iſay.</hi> 10.1. So that in regard of them the knot is looſed, which ſhould binde our conſciences to obedience: for <hi>we ought to obey God rather then men. Act.</hi> 5.29. This is that Law of Order, whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour is the God of Order, and which begets the effect of Order; <hi>Tranquillitatem ordinis: That calme of order:</hi> So Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deſcribes <hi>Dibries,</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> faire daughter</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Shelomith, or Peace.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Euſtath. in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Il. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>A daughter, a faire daughter, beautifull as <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> amiable as <hi>Rebecca,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: mixing ſweet ſmiles with a matrons honour; <hi>Alma Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> a nouriſhing Mother: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the nurſe of youth: the comfort of grey haires. What not? The guift,<note place="margin">Beza in Epiſt. ad Rom. cap. <hi>5.1.</hi>
                  </note> yea <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all the gifts of God to men. She is the bond which ties vs vnto God, to men, and to our ſelues <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Euſtath. in Hom. Il. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> ſayth the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick from knitting vs by charity to God, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordance to our neighbours, and by an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ſelfe-complacencie to our owne ſelues. The Daughter of the Law: <hi>Shelomith,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Dibri.</hi> I remember another woman, <hi>Shelomith,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2006:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> mentioned in holy Writ. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 3.19. and ſhee the daughter of <hi>Zerubbabel.</hi> Whats that?<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The diſperſer of confuſion:<note place="margin">Diſpergere.</note> and who can that be ſaue <hi>Dibri,</hi> that great inſtrument of Order; <hi>Dibri,</hi> the Law? Loe in this alſo the myſterie is continued, <hi>Shelomith</hi> is the daughter of <hi>Dibri,</hi> Peace of the Law. <hi>Shelomith</hi> an <hi>Iſraelitiſh woman,</hi> the daughter of the <hi>couenant,</hi> and ſo of the <hi>Law.</hi> The bleſſing of Gods people: <hi>Peace on Iſrael; Pſalm.</hi> 128.6. a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the rebellious: <hi>There is no peace ſaith the Lord, to the wicked. Iſay.</hi> 48.22. Hee ſayth ſo twice, concluding two Chapters with the ſame <hi>Selah: There is no peace, ſaith my God to the wicked. Iſay.</hi> 57.21. Chriſt choſe to be borne in the <hi>Peace</hi> of the World, and by the embaſſage of an <hi>Angell,</hi> ſent the Peace of God into the World: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">Glarean. in trop. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Peace on earth. Luk.</hi> 2.14. Loe the <hi>bearer</hi> was no leſſe then an Angell, and the <hi>Doner,</hi> the verie Sonne of God. Happie then, thrice happie, yea in the Iewes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Beza in Saint Matth. <hi>10.12,</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>compleately happy is</hi> that bleſſed broode, to whom belongeth that diuine title of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>the ſons of Peace.</hi> O my brethren, know and bluſh. Loe we are they, <hi>Pacem habemus ſine timore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ireneus aduerſ, haereſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in vijs ambulamus, nauigamus quocunque volumus.</hi> So <hi>Irenaeus</hi> deſcribes the peace of his time, of which his <hi>Name</hi> was the Prophet. Let vs at once inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret and applie it. Was euer nation voide of feare? We are more; we haue beene a refuge to the fearefull. Had euer people ſecuritie in their daily iourneys? we haue more: our houſes night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are our Caſtles; yea our open fieldes are free from ciuill and forreine inuaſions was euer Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2006:14"/> rich in Merchandize? we are more; our ſhips haue brought home gold from Ophyr, yea wee haue lent to other Nations. Briefely, our wiues are not rauiſhed; our Virgins are not defloured; the bloud of our Babes is not mixed with their Parents; our grey-haired Fathers cloſe not the eyes of their gaſping ſonnes; there is no crie in our ſtreets: <hi>God hath not dealt ſo with euery Nation.</hi> And what hath now our <hi>Shelomith?</hi> What hath our <hi>Peace</hi> brought foorth? An ougly broode, infinitly diſlike her ſelfe. Alas, a curſer, a blaſphemer, or a thiefe,<note place="margin">Hugo Cardin. in loc. cit.</note> 
                  <hi>which alſo takes Gods name in vaine. Prou.</hi> 30.9. Shee was indeed louely as <hi>Dinah,</hi> but as vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: The one rauiſhed by <hi>Shechem:</hi> The other contracted to a foule Egyptian. Though then the Iſraelitiſh woman bare him, the Egyptian begate him,<note place="margin">Godwin. Moſes &amp; Aaron. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> ex Eurici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. &amp; Aben Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rà in Num. <hi>1.2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Familia matris non voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur familia: The mohers families amongſt the Iewes was eſteemed as no family.</hi> He takes his name from his Father: <hi>He was the ſonne of an Egyptian:</hi> verſ. 10. and though Peace <hi>per accidens,</hi> Accidentally may be ſtiled the mother, yet the procreatour, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getter, the father of ſinne, is that black Egyptian the Deuill. He begets ſinne, not on the Subſtance, but the excrements of Peace: as the beſt beauty may be corrupted, and that corruption ingender wormes. To the euidence of which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to adde one more myſticke Genealogy, <hi>adſtipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that of <hi>Hoſe; Hoſ.</hi> 1. His wife in the viſion was <hi>Gomer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deficere, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumi.</note> 
                  <hi>a Conſumption or Rottenneſſe,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Diblaim, a Cluſter of figges,</hi> the expreſſiue embleme of Plentie: <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.8. Her children, <hi>Izreel, Lo-Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamah,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2006:14"/> and <hi>Lo-Ammi, A Scattered people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Maſſae ficuum.</note> 
                  <hi>an Negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mercy, an Alienation from God.</hi> Thus <hi>peace</hi> procreates <hi>plentie; abuſed plentie, rottenneſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Non miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam conſequi.</note> and <hi>rottenneſſe</hi> the <hi>curſe.</hi> Lo then my brethren, to what a paſſe our tranſgreſſions haue brought vs: Wee haue abuſed Gods plentie vnto rottenneſſe: his gifts vnto immoderate riote and exceſſe, all of vs; the two ſiſters, <hi>Aholah</hi> and <hi>Aholibah, Samaria</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the People and Prieſts haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication with our owne inordinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.3. and <hi>offered vp the gifts of God vnto Baal: Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. euen to that Idol of our own ſenſual concupiſcence. The Romanes <hi>Leges Cibariae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dion. Hiſt. Xiphilin. in Claudio.</note> their frugall ſumptuarie Lawes which moderated hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then feaſts, may rayſe a bluſh of ſhame in the face of vs Chriſtians. Good God what Epicurean cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities are dayly deuiſed by ſluggiſh braines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to labour for nothing but their luſt, to ſatisfie and delight the various luſts of our palates! What more then abundant idle expences, as fooliſh, as vaine, are ſquandered away, euen to the iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that moſt diſſinct and lauiſhly profuſe <hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogable!</hi> When, God knowes, we commit extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our riot: <hi>A nobis extrahitur crudeliter quod conſumitur inaniter,</hi> ſaith a good man in the perſon of the poore; The ouerplus of our eſtates is not ours, but Gods: He giues them to the poore, but we vſurpe them to our own pleaſures, turning our Peace into gluttony, conuerting his Plentie into Luxurie. Theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iud.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Spots in our ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets,</hi> which ſhould be temperate feaſts of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when without feare of God,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2006:15"/> or Magiſtrates, drunkenneſſe is mixed with glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, <hi>and all our tables are full of vomiting: Iſay.</hi> 28.8. Shall we then be any more <hi>Iſrael,</hi> preuailing with God by our prayers? I ſhould ſuppoſe not, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Izreel,</hi> a ſcattered people, ful of bloud. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.8, 11. yea <hi>Lo-Ammi</hi> and <hi>Lo-Ruhamah, None of mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>nor obtaining mercie,</hi> vnto whom thus ſaith the Lord: <hi>Pleade with your mother, pleade with her; for ſhee is not my wife, neither am I her husband, but let her take her fornications out of her ſight and her adulteries from betweene her breaſtes. Leſt I ſtrippe her naked as in the day when ſhee was borne, and make her as a wilderneſſe, and leaue her as a drie land, and ſlay her for thirſt. And I will haue no pittie vpon her children, for they are the children of fornications; Hoſ.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. Their dainty mouthes at laſt muſt bee filled with vnſauoury earth, and their pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered fleſh one day become the cold food of crawling wormes. Temperance commended <hi>Ius nigrum,</hi> a meſſe of thinne blacke water-gruell, as a diet to the famous Spartans, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Naſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Xenophon. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> a ſlender, homelie ſallet of Water-creſſes, for a breakefaſt to the nobleſt Perſians. Rich <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> banquet for three Angels, was but a <hi>piece of fleſh, a meſſe of milke, a diſh of butter and a hearth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cake. Geneſ</hi> 18.6, 7, 8. and part of that royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which prudent <hi>Abigal</hi> beſtowed vpon King <hi>Dauid</hi> and his Chiefetaines to dinner, was <hi>fiue meaſures of parched corne.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.16. What ſhall we doe then with this looſe prodigall, this ſonne of the Egyptian, who ſpends his patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to fill his belly, and, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> his birth-right
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2006:15"/> for a meſſe of pottage: Let him be brought vnto <hi>Moſes, Nigri patiatur carceris vncum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuuenal ſaytr. <hi>13</hi>
                  </note> Let the hand of Iuſtice be vpon him.<note place="margin">Hor. Carm. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ode. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quid triſtes querimoniae Si non ſupplicio culpa reciditur?</hi> The blaſphemer will ſtill curſe, if hee be not puniſhed:<note place="margin">Ouid. meta. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> yea <hi>Pars ſynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra trahetur,</hi> That corrupt member will rotte the bodie. Wherefore <hi>thine eye ſhall not ſpare him. Deut.</hi> 19.13. It is Gods command or he will not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe his owne precepts. The Heathen could confeſſe his Iuſtice to haue <hi>Acrem oculum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heliod. hiſt. Ethiop. lib <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>A ſharpe eye</hi> to note tranſgreſſions, and a heauie hand to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Stolne waters are ſweete but they fill the mouth full of grauell:</hi> for, vnderſtand it of what theft you will, <hi>the dead are there, and her gueſts are in the depth of hell. Prou.</hi> 9.17, 18. The theefe in the Epigramme finding the golden ſworde, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Hee would faine haue beene fingering the gold; Oh but it was a ſword, &amp; it is dangerous medling with edged tooles, let him take heede: <hi>The iſſues thereof are Death. Prou.</hi> 14.12. Indeed he may for a time eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, and ſo make haſte to be rich: but the hand of God, though it bee ſlow, wounds very deepe. The Poet can tell you a Tale worth the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, of a murtherer, who ſlept vnder a rotten wall; hee was warned in a dreame to depart thence: hee ſtarts vp, and was no ſooner out of danger, but the wall fell. He thankes God, as hee had good reaſon to doe, but intertaines a very euill opinion of him, and ſuppoſed, that hee was well pleaſed with his murther. But the next night another viſion certifies him, that he was fouly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2006:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;<note place="margin">Xenoph. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> God was nothing at all delighted with his ſin, neither did he fauour the tranſgreſſour: hee preuented that death, not in pitie to ſaue him, but in venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to keepe him for a worſe and more ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: he preſerued him from the wall, to reſerue him for the gallowes. <hi>None muſt kill Caine, Gen.</hi> 4.15. not becauſe hee ſhould be fauourably preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from death, but becauſe he ſhould be puniſhed and tired with a <hi>Vagabonds</hi> tedious and ſhamefull life, Verſ. 12. Againe, as for the conſeruation of an inuiolate Peace, we muſt abſtaine from wicked deeds; ſo are we no leſſe bound to refraine from iniurious words. One asked <hi>Charillus,</hi> why <hi>Lycur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> gaue ſo few Lawes to the Lacedemonians: he pithily anſwers,<note place="margin">Plutarch. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Becauſe they vſed not many words.</hi> The fewer the offences, the leſſe need of Lawes; and the fewer the words, the fewer the offences: ſith <hi>the hypocrite with his mouth hurts his neighbours, Prou.</hi> 11.8. Wherefore <hi>Dauid</hi> makes no great difference betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a prater, and an vniuſt man. Hee rankes both names in one Text toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their puniſhments: <hi>The backbiter ſhall not be eſtabliſhed on the earth: euill ſhall hunt the cruell man to deſtruction: Pſal.</hi> 140.11. <hi>Yea, God ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him for euer; hee ſhall take him, and plucke him out of his Tabernacle, and roote him out of the Land of the liuing: Pſalm.</hi> 52.5. Loe, what a world of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is inflicted vpon the tongue! Nor is it wonder: for it is <hi>a world of wickedneſſe, yea, a flame of Hell fire: Iam.</hi> 3.6. O then Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2006:16"/> which ſcorneſt Gods Miniſters, and re-crucifieſt the Lord of glory with prophane oathes, and wicked blaſphemies, happy haddeſt thou been, haddeſt thou but knowne the things that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to thy Peace.<note place="margin">Flauius Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus contra Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> The Law-giuer (as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords) forbad the Iewes to blaſpheme the gods of the Nations, though they were but Idoles: and why? Becauſe they were reputed gods. Such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence belongs vnto the very naked eſteeme of a Diuinity. But now (O tremble to receiue what I tremble to relate!) how often may wee heare the moſt ſacred name of God puffed from the blaſphemers mouthes, as often as their Tobacco, or (almoſt) their breath! And yet is no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proportioned to the offence, nor deſtinate to the offendour; or if there be, may we not iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, not executed? This ſinne the Diuell (ſith Nature hath cloathed it with no pleaſure) hath ſeaſoned with a cuſtomary delight. Tis the young Gentlemans eloquence, and I pray God it creepe into no higher titles. Will not my Lord ſweare a greater oath, then a meane Gentleman, yea, and thinke it very proportionate to his Nobilitie? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Suetonius in Veſpaſi.</note> Who ere thou art that vainly ſuppoſeſt by thy greatneſſe to countenance this ſinne; Sir, Sir, remember that when you die, and riſe again, you muſt leaue your Honour behind you, and be a naked man; when ſo many eternall puniſhments muſt be inflicted on thy trembling ſoule, as thou haſt giuen wounds vnto thy bleſſed, but violated Sauiour by wicked oathes, and curſed blaſphemies:<note place="margin">Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2006:17"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when thou darteſt thy curſes to pierce another, they violently recoyle, and wound thine owne ſoule. And though by chance you eſcape the puniſhment of man, yet <hi>The Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine. Exod.</hi> 20.7. And this guilt ſhall ſurely be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, for <hi>A man that vſeth much ſwearing, the Plague ſhall neuer depart from his houſe, &amp;c: Ecclus.</hi> 23.11. <hi>This is that word which is cloathed with death: God grant it be not found in the heritage of our Iacob: but they that feare God wil eſchewe all ſuch, &amp; are not wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſin.</hi> V. 12. Gods vengeance is ſlow, but ſure. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> He delayes long, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will remit all puniſhment, but becauſe in that time of delay he will increaſe and prouide more. For his iudgement (as elegantly <hi>Tertullian</hi>) <hi>Non in compede aut pileo verſatur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de Patient.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed in aeternitate aut poenae aut ſalutis;</hi> doth not repay with momentany retributions, but rewards with eternitie, either of ioy or paine. To conclude then: concerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offences; let him that hath ſinned and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped puniſhment, ſinne no more, leſt a worſe thing happen vnto him. But let the blaſphemer, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious offendour, the ſonne of the Egyptian bee brought vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and let <hi>Moſes</hi> enquire of the Lord, and then in the feare of the Lord execute the Iuſtice of the Lord. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: And you which ſet in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire: <hi>take heede that you iudge righteouſly, leſt the righteous Lord iudge you.</hi> As <hi>Peace</hi> hath brought foorth <hi>tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by a circular generation,</hi> let <hi>tranſgreſsion excite to Iudgement,</hi> that ſo <hi>Dan</hi> may beget <hi>Dibri;</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri,
<pb facs="tcp:2006:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Shelomith;</hi> that <hi>Iudgement</hi> may <hi>procreate</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> beget <hi>a refined Peace.</hi> So ſhall our Land bee cleanſed from the guilt of ſinne, and Peace ſhall bee on Iſrael. Which the God of Peace grant vnto vs, whom yet hee hath continued the ſonnes of Peace, for the Merits, and by the mediation of Ieſus Chriſt the Prince of Peace, to whom with the holy Spirit of conſolation and peace bee aſcribed, as to the onely Author and Source, as all Power, &amp;c. ſo all iuſt Iudgement, vpright Lawes, and perfect Peace, &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
